Chapter 125. The log and line.
While now the faded Peekquad had been so long a float this voyage, the log and
line had but very seldom been in use, owing to a confident reliance on other
means of determining the vessel's place.
Some merchant men and many whalemen, especially when cruising, wholly neglect
to heave the log, though at the same time, and frequently more for form's
sake than anything else, regularly putting down upon the customary slate
the course steered by the ship, as well as the presumed average rate of
progression every hour. It had thus been with the Peekquad. The wooden reel, an
angular log attached, hung long untouched just beneath the railing of
the afterbull works. Rains and spray had damped it. Sun and wind had warped it.
All the elements had combined to rot a thing that hung so idly. But heedless of
all this, his mood seized Ahab, as he happened to glance upon the reel, not
many hours after the magnet scene, and he remembered how his quadrant was no
more, and recalled his frantic oath about the level log and line. The ship
was sailing plungingly, a stern the billows rolled in riots. Forward there, heave the log.
Two seaman came, the golden hued Tahesian and the grizzly mansmen. Take
the real one of you. I'll heave.
They went towards the extreme stern on the ship's le side, where the deck, with
the oblique energy of the wind, was now almost dipping into the creamy sidelong
rushing sea. The mansman took the reel, and holding it high up by the projecting
handle ends of the spindle round which the spool of line revolved, so stood
with the angular log hanging downwards, till Ahab advanced to him. Ahab stood
before him and was lightly unwinding some 30 or 40 turns to form a
preliminary hand coil to toss overboard when the old mansman who was intently
eyeing both him and the line made bold to speak. Sir, I mistrust it. This line
looks far gone. Long heat and wet have spoiled it. It will hold, old gentlemen.
Long heat and wet. Have they spoiled thee? Thou seems to hold, or truer
perhaps, life holds thee, not thou it.
I hold the spool, sir. But just as my captain says, with these gray hairs of
mind is not worthwhile disputing, especially with a superior who will never confess.
What's that? There now is a patched professor in Queen Nature's granite
founded college, but me thinks he's too subservient. Where thou born? In the
little rocky aisle of man, sir.
Excellent. Thoust hit the world by that.
I know not, sir, but I was born there.
In the aisle of man, hey, well, the other way it's good. Here's a man from
man. A man born in once independent man and now unmanned of man which is sucked
in by what? Up with the reel. The dead blind wall butts all inquiring heads at
last. Up with it. So the log was heaved. The loose coils rapidly straightened out in a long
dragging line a stern. And then instantly the reel began to whirl in
turns jerkingly raised and lowered by the rolling billows. The towing
resistance of the log caused the old reelman to stagger strangely.
Hold hard.
Snap. The overstrained line sagged down in one long foon. The tugging log was gone.
I crushed the quadrant. The thunder turns the needles. And now the mad sea
parts the log line, but Ahab can mend all. Haul in there, Tahesian, reel up,
mank. And look ye, let the carpenter make another log, and mend thou the line. See to it.
There he goes now. To him nothing's happened, but to me the skewer seems
loosening out of the middle of the world. All in, all in Tahesian. These
lines run whole and whirling out. Come in broken and dragging slow. Ha! Pip,
come to help. E, Pip. Pip, whom call you Pip? Pip jumped from the whaleboat.
Pip's missing. Let's see now if you haven't fished him up here, fisherman.
It drags hard. I guess he's holding on.
Jerk him, Tahiti. Jerk him off. We haul in no cowards here. Oh, there's his arm
just breaking water. A hatchet. A hatchet. Cut it off. We haul in no
cowards here. Captain Ahab. Sir, sir.
Here's Pip trying to get on board again.
Peace, thou crazy loon, cried the mansman, seizing him by the arm. Away
from the quarter deck. The greater idiot ever scolds the lesser, muttered Ahab,
advancing. Hands off from that holiness.
Where sayest thou Pip was, boy? A stern there, sir. A stern. Lo, low. And who
art thou, boy? I see not my reflection in the vacant pupils of thy eyes. Oh
God, that man should be a thing for immortal souls to siv through. Who art thou, boy?
Bellboy, sir. Ship's crier. Ding dong ding. Pip pip pip. 100 lb of clay reward
for pip. 5 feet high. Looks cowardly.
Quickest known by that. Ding dong ding.
Who's seen Pip the coward?
There can be no hearts above the snow line. Oh, you frozen heavens. Look down
here. Ye did beget this luckless child and have abandoned him. You creative libertines.
Here, boy. Ahab's cabin shall be Pips's home henceforth, while Ahab lives. Thou
touchest my innermost center, boy. Thou art tied to me by cords woven of my heartstrings.
Come, lets down.
What's this? Here's velvet shark skin.
Intently, gazing at Ahab's hand and feeling it. Ah, now had poor Pip but
felt so kind a thing as this, perhaps he had never been lost. This seems to me,
sir, as a man rope, something that weak souls may hold by. Oh, sir, let old
Perth now come and rivet these two hands together, the black one with the white,
for I will not let this go.
Oh boy, nor will I thee, unless I should thereby drag thee to worse horrors than
are here. Come then to my cabin. Lo you believers in gods all goodness and in
man all ill. Lo you see the omnisient gods oblivious of suffering man. And man
though idiotic and knowing not what he does yet full of the sweet things of love and gratitude.
Come. I feel prouder leading thee by thy black hand than though I had grasped an emperor's.
There go two dafted ones now, muttered the old mansman. One dafted with
strength, the other dafted with weakness. But here's the end of the
rotten line, all dripping, too. Mend it, eh? I think we'd best have a new line
altogether. I'll see Mr. Stub about it.